Guide to the Sam Reed Papers, 1986-2001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Sam Reed papers 1986-2001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Reed, Sam, d. 1999.
1.2 Linear Feet Approximately 500 Items
Sam Reed was a community activist and organizer, and the founder of the Trumpet of Conscience newsletter in Durham, North Carolina.
The Sam Reed Papers span the years 1986-2001, and pertain to the political activism of Sam Reed of Durham, North Carolina, particularly in connection with the civil rights movement and subsequent race and labor relations issues in the South. The collection consists of the records of the Durham organization founded by Reed, Trumpet of Conscience, and a run of the newsletter of the same name, 1987-2000. Other papers include correspondence to Reed; biographical information, interviews, speeches, and articles by and about Sam Reed; and awards honoring Reed and the organization he founded. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
Administrative Information
Online Items
Images from this collection are available in Sam Reed and the Trumpet of Conscience - Duke Digital Collections.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Sam Reed Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2009.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1906 Aug. 20 Born Sam Pobiersky in a small Jewish village in the Ukraine
1923 Emigrated to the United States with family and settled in Minnesota
1925 Changed last name to Reed in honor of John Reed, author of Ten Days that Shook the World, a history of the Bolshevik Revolution
1973 Moved to Durham, N.C.
1987 Founded the Trumpet of Conscience newsletter and organization
1999 Elected vice-president of the Durham chapter of the NAACP
1999 Aug. 3 Passed away at the age of 93 in Durham, N.C.
2000 Trumpet of Conscience organization disbanded
Collection Overview
The Sam Reed Papers span the years 1986-2001, and pertain to the political activism of Sam Reed of Durham, North Carolina, particularly in connection with the civil rights movement and subsequent race and labor relations issues in the South. The collection consists of the records of the organization founded by Reed, Trumpet of Conscience, and a run of the newsletter of the same name, 1987-2000. Other papers include correspondence to Reed, interviews, speeches, and articles by and about Sam Reed, and awards honoring Reed and the organization he founded. Topics covered or touched on by these materials include the history of race relations in Durham, North Carolina, and Durham history in general; civil rights actions in North Carolina and Durham; the involvement of Duke University and North Carolina Central students, faculty, and administration in various local events; political action by Durham citizens groups; and, more generally, human rights issues in the South. A selection of materials from the collection have been digitized and are available in Duke Digital Collections. Original audiovisual materials are closed to use; for access, please consult with a reference archivist before coming to use the collection. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
African Americans -- Durham (N.C.)
American Civil Liberties Union of North Carolina
Audiocassettes
Civil rights movements -- Durham (N.C.)
Durham (N.C.) -- History -- 20th century
Durham (N.C.) -- Periodicals
Durham (N.C.) -- Politics and government -- 20th century
Durham (N.C.) -- Race relations -- 20th century
Durham (N.C.) -- Social conditions -- 20th century
DVDs
John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
Labor movement -- North Carolina
North Carolina -- Race relations
Political activists -- Durham (N.C.)
Political participation -- Durham (N.C.)
Reed, Sam, d. 1999
Reed, Sam, d. 1999 -- Interviews
Trumpet of Conscience
Videocassettes
Related Material
Sam Reed and the Trumpet of Conscience
Duke University Libraries Digital Collections.
Contents of Collection
- Sam Reed Papers, 1986-2001, (2 boxes)
  - Articles collected by Sam Reed, 1975-1999 (Box 1)
  - Bill Chafe speech (Box 1)
  - Correspondence to Sam Reed, 1997-1999 (Box 1)
  - Dorothy Brokaw, 1995-1997
    - Trumpet of Conscience newsletters
    - Clippings
    - Negatives
  - Dorothy Brokaw, 1997-2000
  - Durham proclamations, 1995-1997
  - Faith Stories
  - Interview, 1996-1997
  - Joe Bowser, newspaper article, 1997-1999
  - Joe Bowser, papers, 1998-2000
  - Sam Reed obituary, 1999
  - Photographs
  - Trumpet of Conscience
    - Flower, 1990s
    - Goals, agendas, endorsements, 1994-1999
    - Mailing list and sponsors
    - MLK Day, 1997
    - Newsletters, 1987-2000
    - Newspaper articles, 1993-1999 and undated
    - Programs, leaflets, correspondence, 1996-1998
  - Recordings
    - DVD: speech by Sam Reed for the 12th annual MLK Jr. celebration, 1997 Jan. 17
    - Audiocassette: Sam Reed, Operation Goodwill, WFTK radio, 1997
    - CD-ROM: Trumpet of Conscience interviews; Sam Reed biography; Trumpet of Conscience overview; interview by Lois Deloatch, 2008 June
  - Awards and honorary plaques, 1986-2001 (Box 2)
  - Trumpet of Conscience banner (Box 2)